# **PAULO BRUNO SERAFIM**

Deep Reinforcement Learning Researcher | Software Developer

I love to solve challenging problems using my creativity, developing new solutions to relevant and nontrivial assignments. Throughout my experience on different projects, I became a person who not only loves solving problems through innovation but also enjoys writing about them. I like to work close to other people who love what they do, so that we can share our experiences and knowledge.

## **SKILLS**

C/C++ 9 years
Data-Oriented and Object-Oriented C/C++

Computer Graphics 6 years CG, 3D Printing, Computational Geometry, and Geometric Modelling in OpenGL and Qt

Reinforcement Learning 5 years Deep Q-Networks projects in the environments ViZDoom, PySC2, OpenAl Gym, and GymRetro

Python 5 years *ML projects with Numpy, Scikit and Matplotlib* 

Deep Learning 5 years
TensorFlow and Keras in Python

Image Processing and 3 years Computer Vision

OpenCV in C/C++ and Python, Image Segmentation, and OCR

## **LANGUAGES**

Native Speaker

Full Professional Proficiency

FR Limited Professional Proficiency

# SOCIAL

paulobruno.github.io

in linkedin.com/in/pbserafim

github.com/paulobruno

researchgate.net/profile/Paulo-Serafim

cv lattes.cnpq.br/7877766764101416

#### CONTACT

2 1100 Benjamim Brasil, Fortaleza, Brazil

+55 85 999972923

pbrunosousa@gmail.com

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Computer Vision Engineer Sept. 2020 – Present *Instituto Atlântico* 

Working on an R&D Computer Vision project for HP applying Deep Learning to the problems of human segmentation and image matting using TensorFlow. Worked on OCR methods applied to printed text documents. Developed a synthetic document generator using OpenCV in Python, capable of generating hundreds of simulated text documents per minute. Co-leader of the Cognitive Computing study group, focused on Computer Vision, Image Processing, and Reinforcement Learning.

Deep RL Researcher Apr. 2018 - Present CRAb - Computer Graphics, Virtual Reality and Animation

Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) researcher, working with autonomous game agents using TensorFlow and the environments ViZDoom, OpenAl Gym, and Unity ML-Agents. Started a subgroup focused on DRL applications, especially in games and character animation. Co-advisor of one undergraduate, two MSc and one PhD candidate students. Currently working on competition and cooperation with multiagent DRL and analysis of agent performance under different views of the same environment.

Computer Graphics Engineer Feb. 2019 – Aug. 2020 *Instituto Atlântico* 

Worked on R&D projects for HP Labs on 3D printing, applying computer graphics methods for surface and volumetric meshes using C/C++ standard libraries. Developed a new way to build voxelized support structures using algorithms of different areas, like Geometric Modelling and Image Processing, which generated a patent application (2019). Improvement of Genetic Algorithm heuristics applied to a Bin Packing Problem (2020).

Software Developer May 2018 – Feb. 2019 GREat - ASTEF

Developed solutions for fingerprint minutiae extraction and matching focused on high performance, using OpenCV in C++. Implemented a data-oriented C++ version of SourceAFIS, reducing runtime in about 90%. Created a side project using Convolutional Neural Networks for fingerprint ROI segmentation (paper presented at IJCNN 2019). Worked on a Transfer Learning solution to enhance fingerprint images, leading to a higher matching percentage (paper presented at IJCNN 2020). Helped the team with singular point detection using YOLOv4 (paper presented at IWSSIP 2021).

EDUCATION		STUDENTS (CO-ADVISOR)		

MSc – Computer Science Federal University of Ceará (UFC)	Mar. 2016 – Apr. 2018	Halisson Rodrigo	PhD	2020 – Present	
Advisor: Dr. Joaquim Bento Cavalcante Neto		Alexandre Magno	BSc/MSc	2019 – Present	
Thesis: Avaliação da competição no treino de agentes autônomos com Aprendizado Profundo por Reforço em jogos de Tiro em Primeira Pessoa (in		Rômulo Férrer Filho	BSc/MSc	2019 – Present	
Portuguese)  Research on multi-agent competitive		Hyuan Farrapo	BSc	2020 – Present	
Networks using the environment V Quantitative analysis comparing the behav		Anderson Oliveira	BSc/MSc	2017 - 2020	
3Sc – Computer Science ederal University of Ceará (UFC) – Magna C	Jan. 2013 – Dec. 2015	Matheus Cordeiro	BSc	2017 – 2019	
ederai Oniversity of Ceara (OFC) – Magna Cu Worked on hair animation projects usii	ng mass-spring systems and	Eduardo Melo	BSc	2015 – 2017	
OpenGL (2013). Developed research autonomous game agents (2014-2015).		Gabriel Costa	BSc	2015 – 2017	
PUBLICATIONS					
Robust Fingerprint Singular Point Detection using a Single-Stage CNN for Object Detection 28th International Conference on Systems, Signals and Image Processing (IWSSIP)					
Investigating Deep Q-Network Agent Sensibility to Texture Changes on FPS Games  XIX Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)					
Deep Reinforcement Learning em Ambientes Virtuais (in Portuguese)  XXII Symposium on Virtual and Augmented Reality (SVR) - Pre-Symposium Book					
Autonomous Foraging with SARSA-based Deep Reinforcement Learning  XXII Symposium on Virtual and Augmented Reality (SVR)					
Simplificando o Balanceamento de Atributos em RPGs Eletrônicos (in Portuguese)  XIX Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)					
A Novel Approach for Automatic Enhancement of Fingerprint Images via Deep  Transfer Learning  2020 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)					
A Minimal Training Strategy to Play Flappy Bird Indefinitely with NEAT  18th Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)					
A Method based on Convolutional Neural Networks for Fingerprint Segmentation 2019 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)					
Evaluating Competition in Training of Deep Reinforcement Learning Agents in First-Person Shooter Games  17th Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)					
				Nov. 2017	
On the Development of an Autonomous Agent for a 3D First-Person Shooter Game Using Deep Reinforcement Learning  16th Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames)					
Towards Playing a 3D First-Person Shooter Game Using a Classification Deep Neural					
Network Architecture  19th Symposium on Virtual and Augmente	d Reality (SVR 2017)				

19th Symposium on Virtual and Augmented Reality (SVR 2017)